<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Noelmas</title>
    <description>Simple data hackery and reflections on tech for public integrity journalism.</description>
    <link>https://blog.noelmas.net/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://blog.noelmas.net/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
      <item>
        <title>Top 5 workshops from NICAR 2017</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I was lucky enough to attend &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ire.org/nicar/&quot;&gt;NICAR&lt;/a&gt; this year - the largest gathering of data journalists worldwide and all-round geek fest. A mind-boggling array of workshops and events were on offer covering the broad range of techniques used by journalists to investigate and present topics using data. These were my top 5 sessions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/robroc/GIS-with-python&quot;&gt;top 5 Python libraries for working with geospatial data&lt;/a&gt; - A whirlwind tour from Roberto Rocha of the 5 best libraries for building a powerful but efficient workflows for analysing, wrangling and presenting geospatial data. It included easy starter code snippets wrapped up in a single Jupyter/notebook presentation to boot. &lt;a href=&quot;http://geopandas.org/&quot;&gt;Geopandas&lt;/a&gt; is already proving an invaluable tool in my day-to-day. &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/robroc/GIS-with-python&quot;&gt;https://github.com/robroc/GIS-with-python&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Michelle Borkin’s talk on the cognition of data visualisation based on a large scale experiment which tracked the responses, recall and eye-movements of volunteers exposed to hundreds of static infographics and charts. Some of the findings were surprising and counter to the lauded Tufte’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.infovis-wiki.net/index.php/Data-Ink_Ratio&quot;&gt;data-ink ratio paradigm&lt;/a&gt;. For instance, Borkin found that information redundnacy in charts positively influenced particiapnts’ recall and understanding. The whole dataset for the project including has been released for openly as the &lt;a href=&quot;http://massvis.mit.edu/&quot;&gt;Massvis Dataset&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A quick introduction to &lt;a href=&quot;https://flourish.studio/&quot;&gt;Kiln’s Flourish Studio&lt;/a&gt;. Kiln founder Duncan Clarke demoed the new platform for publishing interactive data visualisations that combines re-usability, clean GUI interfaces for data updating whilst allowing for radical creativity in the design process.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Buzzfeed’s Open Labs Fellows’ crash course in mining data from social media sources including Facebook and Twitter with a handy &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/buzzfeed-openlab/big-picture/wiki/Guide:-Harvesting-social-data&quot;&gt;Github repo&lt;/a&gt; of scripts to get you started on coding up your own scrapers. &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/buzzfeed-openlab/big-picture/wiki/Guide:-Harvesting-social-data&quot;&gt;https://github.com/buzzfeed-openlab/big-picture/wiki/Guide:-Harvesting-social-data&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Neil Halloran - the creator of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://vimeo.com/128373915&quot;&gt;Fallen of World War II’s&lt;/a&gt; - gave wide-ranging talk on the natural tension between statistics and sentiment and how we can do a better job at marrying gate two. Including some great links to further reading that I will follow up on: Steven Pinker’s &lt;em&gt;The Better Angels of Our Nature&lt;/em&gt; and Daniel Kahneman’s &lt;em&gt;Thinking, Fast &amp;amp; Slow&lt;/em&gt;. Here’s a link to the amazing visual data story if you haven’t seen it already:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://player.vimeo.com/video/128373915&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;360&quot; frameborder=&quot;100&quot; align=&quot;center&quot; webkitallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; mozallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://vimeo.com/128373915&quot;&gt;The Fallen of World War II&lt;/a&gt; from &lt;a href=&quot;https://vimeo.com/user22627560&quot;&gt;Neil Halloran&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href=&quot;https://vimeo.com&quot;&gt;Vimeo&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chrys Wu has helpfully pulled together the various tip sheets and slide decks from some of the other sessions: &lt;a href=&quot;http://blog.chryswu.com/2017/03/02/nicar17-slides-links-tutorials-nicar17/&quot;&gt;http://blog.chryswu.com/2017/03/02/nicar17-slides-links-tutorials-nicar17/&lt;/a&gt;. If you’re interested in getting involved there is a very active disucssion list &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ire.org/resource-center/listservs/subscribe-nicar-l/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Massive thanks to all the organisers and stalwarts of the Nicar community for facilitating such a brilliant exchange of stories, skills and knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 09 Mar 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://blog.noelmas.net/data-journalism/2017/03/09/nicar-2017/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.noelmas.net/data-journalism/2017/03/09/nicar-2017/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Mining the UK register of beneficial ownership</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;UK companies with hidden owners lie behind some of the worst problems of our time. Amongst other things they have been used to breach UN sanctions, evade taxes and rip off ordinary citizens. That’s why Global Witness has been calling for an end to these getaway cars for crime and corruption for years (see this &lt;a href=&quot;http://ed.ted.com/lessons/how-exposing-anonymous-companies-could-cut-down-on-crime-global-witness&quot;&gt;TED-Ed animation&lt;/a&gt; for a short introduction to the issue). Now, we’re seeing the first seeds of change - in June, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://companieshouse.blog.gov.uk/2016/04/13/the-new-people-with-significant-control-register/&quot;&gt;UK government started publishing&lt;/a&gt; the world’s first open data register of the real owners and controllers of companies – known as “beneficial owners”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is a big step forward for transparency in this country, and a potential treasure trove of information - but we need to make sense of it first. Which is why we’ve collaborated with &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.datakind.org/chapters/datakind-uk&quot;&gt;DataKind UK&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://opencorporates.com/&quot;&gt;OpenCorporates&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.spendnetwork.com/&quot;&gt;Spend Network&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.occrp.org/en&quot;&gt;OCCRP&lt;/a&gt;, to probe it in detail, and give feedback on how useful it is. So on a grey autumn weekend in London, we brought together thirty volunteer data scientists, including the head of software for a Formula 1 team, an astrophysicist and a former consultant to the UK tax authority.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We had three aims for the weekend. Firstly, we wanted to get some basic insights into this data and what it could tell us about companies in the UK. Secondly, it was important to understand the flaws and gaps in the new register. Finally, we were curious to see whether the register could yield investigative leads.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s a snapshot of what we found:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Almost 3,000 companies listed their beneficial owner as a company with a tax haven address - something that is not allowed under the rules. There are problems with how the data has been inputted. For example, you can write anything in the nationality field and we found over 500 ways of putting “British”, including ten people who wrote “Cornish”.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;76 beneficial owners share the same name and birthday as someone on the U.S. sanctions list. We have to do more digging to find out whether these are actually the same people, but it’s an insight into what is possible with this new information.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Most beneficial owners are from the UK, followed by a number from other European countries and India and China.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;insights&quot;&gt;Insights&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The data allows us to start to understand the complex ecosystem of companies and their owners in the UK - where they’re from, and what other companies they own. In theory, law enforcement agencies, journalists and civil society being able to map this stuff out will make it much harder for those with something to hide to do so behind layers and layers of secret companies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under the new system, companies have to provide ownership information once a year when they send in their annual return or “confirmation statement”. Out of 3.5 million companies, 1.3 million have already filed beneficial ownership information as of 17 November. Most beneficial owners (1.2 million) are British. Perhaps unsurprisingly when you take the British out of the mix, Irish is the next biggest nationality, followed by a mix of European countries (Italy and Poland) and the two mega-economies of China and India.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.globalwitness.org//media/images/Screen_Shot_2016-11-19_at_22.07.18.width-1280.png&quot; alt=&quot;Beneficial Owners Nationality&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Nationality of beneficial owners in the UK register&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On top of nationality, we also have information on where beneficial owners live. The vast majority are based in the UK, with 183,000, or 13% of the total, living overseas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the arguments made against creating these registers is that companies would find it very difficult to identify their beneficial owners, but this doesn’t appear to be the case. In only 2% of cases did companies say that they were struggling to identify a beneficial owner or collect the right information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just under ten percent of companies claimed to have no beneficial owner. This is possible under the legislation, because you have to own at least 25 percent of a company to be considered its beneficial owner. We think that’s quite a high threshold, which could be exploited by people looking to stay under the radar So we will be digging a bit deeper to see whether companies are trying to avoid disclosing information that they should be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;max-width:900px&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe id=&quot;datawrapper-chart-EVcm0&quot; src=&quot;//datawrapper.dwcdn.net/EVcm0/1/&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowtransparency=&quot;true&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;allowfullscreen&quot; webkitallowfullscreen=&quot;webkitallowfullscreen&quot; mozallowfullscreen=&quot;mozallowfullscreen&quot; oallowfullscreen=&quot;oallowfullscreen&quot; msallowfullscreen=&quot;msallowfullscreen&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;196&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;&quot;undefined&quot;==typeof window.datawrapper&amp;&amp;(window.datawrapper={}),window.datawrapper[&quot;EVcm0&quot;]={},window.datawrapper[&quot;EVcm0&quot;].embedDeltas={&quot;100&quot;:196,&quot;200&quot;:196,&quot;300&quot;:196,&quot;400&quot;:196,&quot;500&quot;:196,&quot;600&quot;:196,&quot;700&quot;:196,&quot;800&quot;:196,&quot;900&quot;:196,&quot;1000&quot;:196},window.datawrapper[&quot;EVcm0&quot;].iframe=document.getElementById(&quot;datawrapper-chart-EVcm0&quot;),window.datawrapper[&quot;EVcm0&quot;].iframe.style.height=window.datawrapper[&quot;EVcm0&quot;].embedDeltas[Math.min(1e3,Math.max(100*Math.floor(window.datawrapper[&quot;EVcm0&quot;].iframe.offsetWidth/100),100))]+&quot;px&quot;,window.addEventListener(&quot;message&quot;,function(a){if(&quot;undefined&quot;!=typeof a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;])for(var b in a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;])&quot;EVcm0&quot;==b&amp;&amp;(window.datawrapper[&quot;EVcm0&quot;].iframe.style.height=a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;][b]+&quot;px&quot;)});&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Approximately 30 beneficial owners have been successfully granted the right to keep their name off the register due to concerns about their security.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We were also able to build up a picture of company networks. These were only partial insights as we were working with just three months’ worth of data, but it gave us an idea of what was possible, and to start to understand complex corporate structures. Complexity doesn’t necessarily indicate wrongdoing. For example below is a partial map of Reckitt Benckiser, the healthcare company that makes Durex condoms among other things. However, it will provide a much better map of how UK companies structure themselves, and in some cases connections between companies may raise further questions about what they have been up to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.globalwitness.org//media/images/Screen_Shot_2016-11-18_at_14.31.23.width-1280.png&quot; alt=&quot;Reckitt Benckiser&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;The UK control structure of Reckitt Benckiser&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;flaws&quot;&gt;Flaws&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Inevitably with a bold experiment like this, there will be problems with the data, despite the generally excellent job that Companies House has done. The flaws that we identified split into two categories: messy data due to how it was collected, and examples of what look like non-compliance with the law.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the big problems we found was that Companies House allows for free text entry for a number of fields. For example, we found over 500 different ways of putting “British”. Our favourite were the 10 beneficial owners who described themselves as Cornish. We were able to get around this by creating a nationality mapping table. However, an easy way to avoid this would be for Companies House to use drop down menus for fields such as nationality or title, with a potential “other box”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.globalwitness.org/media/images/Screen_Shot_2016-11-18_at_14.19.07.width-1280.png&quot; alt=&quot;Many ways of spelling British&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;The many ways of spelling “British” in the UK beneficial ownership register&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another big challenge is the lack of unique identifiers for individuals and some companies. We were relying on using name and day and month of birth to try and identify individuals. This is fine if you’re someone with an unusual name, but proves more tricky for the John Smiths or Mohammed Iqbals of this world. We’d like to work with Companies House on thinking about how they could get around this problem. One solution could be to assign beneficial owners a unique number to allow better cross-matching.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were also 2,160 beneficial owners born in 2016. Now either these are a very precocious bunch of toddlers or the data has been entered incorrectly. We also had people who listed 9988 as their year of birth - clearly a visitor from the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On top of these data validation issues, we found a number of signs of non-compliance with the law. For example, 9,800 companies listed their beneficial owner as a foreign company. Now this is possible if the foreign company was listed on one of the stock exchanges deemed equivalent to the UK system (e.g. the US, EU and Japanese exchanges). However, we found almost 3,000 companies with tax haven addresses listed as beneficial owners. This is not allowed under the rules. We’ll be handing this list of companies over to Companies House to investigate further.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;max-width:900px&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe id=&quot;datawrapper-chart-OpOKm&quot; src=&quot;//datawrapper.dwcdn.net/OpOKm/1/&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowtransparency=&quot;true&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;allowfullscreen&quot; webkitallowfullscreen=&quot;webkitallowfullscreen&quot; mozallowfullscreen=&quot;mozallowfullscreen&quot; oallowfullscreen=&quot;oallowfullscreen&quot; msallowfullscreen=&quot;msallowfullscreen&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;351&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;&quot;undefined&quot;==typeof window.datawrapper&amp;&amp;(window.datawrapper={}),window.datawrapper[&quot;OpOKm&quot;]={},window.datawrapper[&quot;OpOKm&quot;].embedDeltas={&quot;100&quot;:485,&quot;200&quot;:418,&quot;300&quot;:385,&quot;400&quot;:385,&quot;500&quot;:351,&quot;600&quot;:351,&quot;700&quot;:351,&quot;800&quot;:351,&quot;900&quot;:351,&quot;1000&quot;:351},window.datawrapper[&quot;OpOKm&quot;].iframe=document.getElementById(&quot;datawrapper-chart-OpOKm&quot;),window.datawrapper[&quot;OpOKm&quot;].iframe.style.height=window.datawrapper[&quot;OpOKm&quot;].embedDeltas[Math.min(1e3,Math.max(100*Math.floor(window.datawrapper[&quot;OpOKm&quot;].iframe.offsetWidth/100),100))]+&quot;px&quot;,window.addEventListener(&quot;message&quot;,function(a){if(&quot;undefined&quot;!=typeof a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;])for(var b in a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;])&quot;OpOKm&quot;==b&amp;&amp;(window.datawrapper[&quot;OpOKm&quot;].iframe.style.height=a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;][b]+&quot;px&quot;)});&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With all of these examples it’s not clear whether this is because the people filing the information didn’t understand the new system, or whether there’s something more sinister going on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;investigation&quot;&gt;Investigation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the key arguments in favour of creating this register was that law enforcement, civil society and journalists could use it to uncover wrongdoing. We didn’t expect to find any slam dunk cases in just a weekend, but we did find a few interesting leads. Because the UK register is available as open data, we could compare it to other data sets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Initial findings suggest 19 senior politicians (known as politically exposed persons), 76 people from the U.S. sanctions list and 267 disqualified directors were listed as beneficial owners.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, these matches were based on name and month and year of birth. This means that it’s hard to be certain that the matches are good ones. Any leads coming out of the new register will have to be followed up with more traditional investigative digging.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also had an initial look at comparing the beneficial ownership to government spending information. It was challenging given that a lot of the spending information doesn’t have proper identification for companies (for example it would be good to include company numbers). But we did find a number of recipients of government contracts who had beneficial owners based in tax havens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;reflections&quot;&gt;Reflections&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As campaigners who have worked for years to get this information out in the public domain, the weekend was an exciting first opportunity to get our hands dirty and start to tell some stories. The work was only possible because the UK government made the decision to make the register free and accessible to all as open data. This is an important lesson for other countries who are thinking about creating similar registers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Inevitably the data was messy, partly due to how the register is set up and partly due to confusion from those providing data. We’re going to be working with Companies House on ironing out some of these issues. Hopefully as the register beds in, these kinks will get ironed out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A big question that we weren’t able to answer was whether people had lied to the register or provided inaccurate information. This is going to be a serious challenge for the credibility of the register, and the government will have to provide more reassurances on how they’re going to ensure data accuracy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, we’re hoping that other governments will see the potential of what the UK has done. The process will be difficult, but if our weekend showed us anything, it’s that this is incredibly useful information to have.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 22 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://blog.noelmas.net/open/data/2016/11/22/data-dive-beneficial-ownership/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.noelmas.net/open/data/2016/11/22/data-dive-beneficial-ownership/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Why we published the data behind Hostile Takeover</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This blog post was originally posted on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.globalwitness.org/en/blog/why-we-published-data-behind-hostile-takeover/&quot;&gt;Global Witness website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It will come as no shock to Cambodians that their ruling elite has amassed vast fortunes whilst in power. As our report, &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.globalwitness.org/en/reports/hostile-takeover/&quot;&gt;Hostile Takeover&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, shows, members of Prime Minister Hun Sen’s family have business interests spanning the majority of the country’s major industries. While 40% of Cambodians live below or close to the poverty line, the Hun family have a combined wealth estimated to total between US$ 500 million and US$ 1 billion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But until fairly recently it has been extremely difficult for activists and campaigners to prove this with hard facts and solid data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This has enabled the country’s most powerful family to continue to line its pockets behind a wall of secrecy. It has also allowed international companies and investors to establish business relationships with members of Hun Sen’s family, either unaware of or unconcerned by previous allegations of corruption and human rights abuses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;limitations-of-the-original-dataset&quot;&gt;Limitations of the original dataset&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The publication of data by &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.moc.gov.kh/en-us/&quot;&gt;Cambodia’s Ministry of Commerce&lt;/a&gt; was a step towards greater transparency. The data held the key to the extensive business interests of Cambodia’s ruling elite, exposing just how much of a grip Hun Sen and his family have over the nation’s economy. However, in its original form the data was unusable for investigative purposes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whilst we commend the Ministry of Commerce for publishing the data in the first place, the information provided suffered from a number of issues that prevented our researchers from using it effectively:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The database was put behind a login, making it difficult to programmatically access&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The search portal didn’t allow people to download the dataset in its entirety&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The service and availability of information changed from time to time. This posed a risk to our research that data would be taken offline or modified without our knowledge. Since the publication of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.globalwitness.org/en/reports/hostile-takeover/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Hostile Takeover&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; report - for instance - shareholder information has been removed completely&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Ministry’s servers were slow and unreliable, making it difficult to conduct in-depth research&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given these limitations we extracted the contents of the database and developed our own version with the functionality needed to support in-depth investigation. This is known as “web scraping” by techies, and it is becoming an essential process in a wide-range of investigations at Global Witness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;open-data-and-network-effects&quot;&gt;Open data and network effects&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At Global Witness we passionately believe that our investigations should be a platform for change. We are well aware, however, that the kinds of changes we want to see can only be achieved when we work through networks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When it comes to data and technology this means enabling a range of actors - from civil society groups to law enforcement - to use the databases we’ve built up and the technology we’ve developed to verify our findings and spot things we haven’t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is exactly what we did for &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.globalwitness.org/en/reports/hostile-takeover/&quot;&gt;Hostile Takeover&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;. We have published both the &lt;a href=&quot;https://cambodiacorporates.globalwitness.org/&quot;&gt;dataset that we extracted&lt;/a&gt; from the Ministry of Commerce in its entirety and also &lt;a href=&quot;https://cambodiacorporates.globalwitness.org/&quot;&gt;the research tool&lt;/a&gt; we developed to interrogate this information including the underlying &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/Global-Witness/cambodia-corporates&quot;&gt;source code&lt;/a&gt;. We have applied &lt;a href=&quot;http://opendefinition.org/&quot;&gt;open licenses&lt;/a&gt; to all of these so anyone can freely access, remix and build on our work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cambodian newspaper &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.phnompenhpost.com/&quot;&gt;The Phnom Penh Post&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; made great use of the data almost immediately after we launched our report. As well as publishing their own analysis of the data we provided, they also produced a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.phnompenhpost.com/national/inside-hun-familys-business-empire#interactive&quot;&gt;playful interactive&lt;/a&gt; letting readers explore the wide-ranging business interests of the Hun Sen family.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.phnompenhpost.com/national/inside-hun-familys-business-empire&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.globalwitness.org/media/images/Screen_Shot_2016-08-19_at_10.17.02.width-500.png&quot; alt=&quot;Cambodia Wheel of Fortune&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By publishing our data openly we also want it to be re-used in some of the game-changing aggregation and search services being built by civic-hackers and tech-for-good enterprises like &lt;a href=&quot;https://opencorporates.com/&quot;&gt;OpenCorporates&lt;/a&gt;. Powerful, free tools for investigative journalists like &lt;a href=&quot;https://data.occrp.org/&quot;&gt;data.occrp.org&lt;/a&gt; benefit hugely from organisations choosing to open their data post-publication.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These tools and this pooling of information is ever more important for anti-corruption campaigners who - in their attempts to unravel global illicit financial flows - need to be able to join the dots between fragmented and siloed datasets. In the same way that medical researchers across the world leverage the technology, data and methods of their peers to defeat deadly diseases, the fight against corruption could benefit from a far more joined up investigative community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But openness isn’t just a practical matter for us, it’s also a principle. As an organisation that asks governments and companies around the world to do more of their work in the open where it can be scrutinised by the public, we believe that once we’ve published a story, and where no risks exist for our sources, we should publish the data we’ve collected as permissibly as possible. We invite others to verify our findings and scrutinise our methodology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;cambodia-corporates-functionality&quot;&gt;Cambodia Corporates functionality&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://cambodiacorporates.globalwitness.org/&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.globalwitness.org//media/images/Screen_Shot_2016-08-19_at_10.19.11.width-800.png&quot; alt=&quot;Cambodia Corporates screnshot&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As well as being able to conduct searches for companies and directors, &lt;a href=&quot;https://cambodiacorporates.globalwitness.org/&quot;&gt;Cambodia Corporates&lt;/a&gt; has a number of functions not available on the original site:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Fuzzy search for names - It’s a common problem in many datasets that names for the same person are spelt differently on different records. This is particularly problematic in cases where names have been. transliterated from Roman script. &lt;a href=&quot;https://cambodiacorporates.globalwitness.org/&quot;&gt;Cambodia Corporates&lt;/a&gt; let’s you introduce “fuzziness” into your search by choosing the number of characters that the results can vary from your original search term&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Find the nationality of chairpersons - The Ministry of Commerce website doesn’t allow you to look at the nationality of the chairperson of Cambodian registered companies. This is important information for understanding international investment in the country.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Download all the data - There are many colleagues and researchers out there who will want to do things with the information that we haven’t anticipated. Perhaps they will want to combine it with other databases they are building. We also want to enable those building excellent registries and search tools like &lt;a href=&quot;https://opencorporates.com&quot;&gt;OpenCorproates&lt;/a&gt; and OCCRP (&lt;a href=&quot;http://data.occrp.org&quot;&gt;data.occrp.org&lt;/a&gt;) to connect to this information.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/Global-Witness/cambodia-corporates&quot;&gt;Get the source code&lt;/a&gt; - For the geeks amongst you, you can download, tweak and re-deploy our source code for similar projects.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Following the publication of &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.globalwitness.org/en/reports/hostile-takeover/&quot;&gt;Hostile Takeover&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; the Ministry of Commerce database no longer contains the shareholder data that our investigation was built on. The reasons as to why this data is no longer available are &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cambodiadaily.com/news/government-scrubs-database-exposed-hun-family-riches-116772/&quot;&gt;unclear&lt;/a&gt;. This important information is currently only available from &lt;a href=&quot;https://cambodiacorporates.globalwitness.org/&quot;&gt;Cambodia Corporates&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can access the fully functional research tool and the attached database of companies and directors at &lt;a href=&quot;https://cambodiacorproates.globalwitness.org&quot;&gt;https://cambodiacorproates.globalwitness.org&lt;/a&gt;, the underlying source code is available on GitHub &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/Global-Witness/cambodia-corporates&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 09 Aug 2016 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>https://blog.noelmas.net/open/data/2016/08/09/hostile-takeover-data/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.noelmas.net/open/data/2016/08/09/hostile-takeover-data/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>A quick look at offshore property ownership in England &amp; Wales</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The ownership of properties and land in England and Wales by companies registered in overseas countries has come under significant scrutiny in recent months. Reports by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.globalwitness.org/en/campaigns/corruption-and-money-laundering/mystery-baker-street/&quot;&gt;Global Witness&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/picturegalleries/uknews/8340483/A-look-round-the-London-house-thought-to-be-owned-by-Libyas-Saif-al-Islam-Gaddafi.html&quot;&gt;The Telegraph&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.theguardian.com/uk-news/2015/mar/04/uk-properties-held-by-offshore-firms-used-in-global-corruption-say-police&quot;&gt;The Guardian&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.private-eye.co.uk/registry&quot;&gt;Private Eye&lt;/a&gt; have shown that offshore ownership can be a convenient means to launder the proceeds of crime and corruption. As it turns out, it is also a convenient mechanism to avoid tax assocaited with buying and selling a property.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.saplaw.co.uk/uk-legal-services/commercial-lawyers-london/commercial-lawyers-articles/using-an-offshore-company-to-buy-and-sell-uk-residential-property&quot;&gt;telling article&lt;/a&gt; on the website of a UK based solicitors lists the potential “tax advantages” of this approach to trading UK property. I quote directly from &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.saplaw.co.uk/uk-legal-services/commercial-lawyers-london/commercial-lawyers-articles/using-an-offshore-company-to-buy-and-sell-uk-residential-property&quot;&gt;the site&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“Regardless of who owns the property any rental income will remain taxable in the UK. If the property is owned by an offshore company only the basic rate of UK income tax (20%) will apply regardless of the level of income.”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“A property can be sold by selling the shares in the company with no UK Capital Gains Tax.”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“If the property is in the name of an individual then on their death inheritance tax is potentially payable on the net value of the property.”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“No stamp duty land tax is payable by a buyer of the shares in the company.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Considering that we’re in the midst of a housing crisis, and with tenants in London paying on average &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.theguardian.com/money/2015/jul/16/tenants-in-england-spend-half-their-pay-on-rent&quot;&gt;72% of their gross income&lt;/a&gt;, the fact that so much property is not subject to normal UK tax law seems particualrly unjust.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I looked at the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gov.uk/guidance/land-registry-overseas-companies-data&quot;&gt;data published by the Land Registry in March 2016&lt;/a&gt;. It contains information on all freeholds and leasholds owned by companies registered overseas. The data is accurate as of 31st October 2015. It contains almost 100,000 leaseholds addresses and includes information on tenure, date of purchase, price paid and if there are multiple owners. This data was made available in response to increasing pressue from civil society groups for greater transparency in the property market and some well-publicised &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.private-eye.co.uk/registry&quot;&gt;Freedom of Information requests concerning the extent of offshore ownership of land and property in England and Wales&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;little-data-available-on-price-but-as-an-estimate&quot;&gt;Little data available on price, but as an estimate…&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We know from this information that at least £10.1 billion of land and property is owned by overseas company. Considering that only 7% of these properties contains price paid data, that’s a staggering figure. We can only approximate what the total value might be for all leaseholds and freeholds in the database. Given that the average price of these freeholds and leasholds is £1,512,032 we might expect the total figure to be around the £150 billion mark. This is substantially higher than the esimate given by the Financial Times in 2015 of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ft.com/cms/s/0/6cb11114-18aa-11e4-a51a-00144feabdc0.html#axzz46ls5rtpE&quot;&gt;£122 billion&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&quot;//datawrapper.dwcdn.net/cxBIK/1/&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowtransparency=&quot;true&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;allowfullscreen&quot; webkitallowfullscreen=&quot;webkitallowfullscreen&quot; mozallowfullscreen=&quot;mozallowfullscreen&quot; oallowfullscreen=&quot;oallowfullscreen&quot; msallowfullscreen=&quot;msallowfullscreen&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;400&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;its-about-secrecy-and-tax&quot;&gt;It’s about secrecy and tax&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take a look at the top 10 countries through which these properties are owned. These are the archetypal tax havens and secrecy jursidictions. Half of them rank in the top 20 most secretive jurisdictions in &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.financialsecrecyindex.com/introduction/fsi-2015-results&quot;&gt;Tax Justice Network’s Financial Secrecy Index&lt;/a&gt;. This quite clearly is not about foreign nationals and normal overseas companies owning property in England and Wales, but rather the deliberate choice to use jurisidctions renowned for low tax rates and corproate secrecy to buy and sell property.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&quot;//datawrapper.dwcdn.net/JNsPc/1/&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowtransparency=&quot;true&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;allowfullscreen&quot; webkitallowfullscreen=&quot;webkitallowfullscreen&quot; mozallowfullscreen=&quot;mozallowfullscreen&quot; oallowfullscreen=&quot;oallowfullscreen&quot; msallowfullscreen=&quot;msallowfullscreen&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;343&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-vast-majority-of-overseas-ownership-is-in-greater-london&quot;&gt;The vast majority of overseas ownership is in Greater London&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unsurprisingly, overseas ownership of property and land is concentrated in the South East and Greater London.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&quot;//datawrapper.dwcdn.net/AFgqt/1/&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowtransparency=&quot;true&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;allowfullscreen&quot; webkitallowfullscreen=&quot;webkitallowfullscreen&quot; mozallowfullscreen=&quot;mozallowfullscreen&quot; oallowfullscreen=&quot;oallowfullscreen&quot; msallowfullscreen=&quot;msallowfullscreen&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;433&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;discredited-companies-use-overseas-ownership-extensively&quot;&gt;Discredited companies use overseas ownership extensively&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A quick look at the top 5 companies that make most extensive use of offshore purchasing of land, we see that one of them, Profitable Plots, has been caught up in &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.telegraph.co.uk/finance/property/news/7436428/Green-Belt-housing-scheme-promoted-by-footballers-leaves-investors-in-the-red.html&quot;&gt;a scandal that involved cheating investors for just short of a million dollars&lt;/a&gt;. Clearly not all people who use offshore property ownership are out to scam, but the level of secrecy afforded to companies incorporated in places like the British Virgin Islands is an invitation to all sorts of nefarious activity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&quot;//datawrapper.dwcdn.net/r3b24/3/&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowtransparency=&quot;true&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;allowfullscreen&quot; webkitallowfullscreen=&quot;webkitallowfullscreen&quot; mozallowfullscreen=&quot;mozallowfullscreen&quot; oallowfullscreen=&quot;oallowfullscreen&quot; msallowfullscreen=&quot;msallowfullscreen&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;413&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 23 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>https://blog.noelmas.net/2016/04/23/offshore-property-analysis/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.noelmas.net/2016/04/23/offshore-property-analysis/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Something is rotten in the state of Denmark</title>
        <description>&lt;div class=&quot;aligned intro&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;rich-text&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;b&gt;Originally posted at on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://globalwitness.org/en/blog/something-rotten-state-denmark/&quot;&gt;Global Witness blog&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;A compelling new Danish drama does a stellar job at portraying some of the mechanisms of corruption that we at Global Witness are all too familiar with.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;aligned&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;rich-text&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;We’re big fans of the new Danish TV series &lt;i&gt;Follow the Money&lt;/i&gt;. It’s a great piece of drama, but we’re also fascinated because it’s a case of fiction mirroring reality right now.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;For anyone following our work, the script used in &lt;i&gt;Follow the Money&lt;/i&gt; will be familiar. A small set of wealthy individuals use the secrecy afforded by offshore jurisdictions to hide and channel illicit funds at the expense of everyday people and investors.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://globalwitness.org/media/images/Energreen.width-300.png&quot; align=&quot;right&quot; width=&quot;300&quot; height=&quot;213&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;/&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;aligned&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;rich-text&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;It tells another important story, which often gets lost. Corruption isn’t something that just affects fragile states and dictatorships, it’s far closer to home than many Western governments like to admit. As our work has shown time and time again, Western companies, law firms and banks are key enablers for moving dirty cash around the world and covering up secret deals, and their governments could be doing much more to put a stop to it.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In fact Denmark seems like the perfect setting to make this point.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Number one in &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.transparency.org/cpi2015&quot;&gt;Transparency International’s Corruption Perceptions Index&lt;/a&gt; in 2015, Denmark does not suffer from the kind of grand corruption that plagues those at the bottom of the Index like Cambodia or Afghanistan. However, such is the structure of the global financial system today, Danish companies and citizens, like those in any other European country, can use networks of offshore subsidiaries to hide and launder illicit funds whilst retaining the veneer of corporate respectability that being based in a center of global finance affords.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Services offered in places like the British Virgin Islands and the Cayman Islands can be used to hide wealth from tax authorities, deceive law enforcement agencies and introduce huge levels of risk to unwitting investors. We’ve seen some these mechanisms at play in our recent investigations into the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.globalwitness.org/en/campaigns/corruption-and-money-laundering/mystery-baker-street/&quot;&gt;London property market&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.globalwitness.org/en/campaigns/oil-gas-and-mining/shell-and-enis-misadventures-nigeria/&quot;&gt;acquisition of one of West Africa’s largest oil blocks&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The fictional, cut-throat energy firm at the heart of the plot, Energreen, uses a number of these ploys to devastating effect. Below are three of the top ways in which its activities mirror the companies we often investigate:&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://ed.ted.com/lessons/how-exposing-anonymous-companies-could-cut-down-on-crime-global-witness&quot;&gt;Anonymous shell companies&lt;/a&gt; are the currency of the corrupt&lt;/b&gt; - Energreen and its insider traders use a network of subsidiaries whose true owners are hidden in order to siphon off funds and fraudulently pump up the value of its own assets.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Secrecy jurisdictions and tax havens such as the British Virgin Islands and the Cayman Islands are conduits for illicit financial flows&lt;/b&gt; - The network of subsidiaries used by Energreen are often based in offshore secrecy jurisdictions deliberately obscuring critical information about the company from law enforcement, the public and investors.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Corruption affects us all&lt;/b&gt; - Energreen’s eventual collapse after it goes public leaves a huge range of investors exposed including pension funds used by everyday people.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;As we wrote &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.globalwitness.org/en/press-releases/david-cameron-majority-british-public-want-you-act-tax-havens/&quot;&gt;two weeks ago&lt;/a&gt; this is a problem that the UK can help to fix by taking action on the UK Territories. For our readers based in the UK, you can watch all 10 episodes of &lt;i&gt;Follow the Money&lt;/i&gt; on &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bbc.co.uk/programmes/b072h7rk&quot;&gt;BBC iPlayer&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 22 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>https://blog.noelmas.net/2016/04/22/follow-the-money/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.noelmas.net/2016/04/22/follow-the-money/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Google Trends in tax avoidance and tax evasion</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The Panama Leaks have shaken the foundations of British politics and done substantial reputational damage to a range of high-profile personalities around the world. We’ve seen plenty of revelations concerning corrupt and morally questionable practices of political elites over the past few years from ICIJ’s Offshore Leaks to the Wikileaks Diplomatic Cables, but few have piqued the interest of the public in the way the Panama Leaks have. Google summed this up nicely in the following chart measuring searches for two of the most significant leaks in recent years:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot; src=&quot;https://ssl.gstatic.com/trends_nrtr/480_RC06/embed_loader.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;
trends.embed.renderWidget(&quot;GB_cu_rWzp4FMBAAAXDM_en&quot;, &quot;fe_line_chart_1752a923-477e-48a9-8e0f-02d189530086&quot;, {&quot;guestPath&quot;:&quot;https://www.google.co.uk:443/trends/embed/&quot;});
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Right-wing newspapers that normally shy away from articles on tax justice have covered the Leaks at length often leading with them on their front page. As an anti-corruption campaigner, I’m hopeful that these revelations could turn the tide of public opinion on key issues around corporate accountability and tax justice. Both are issues that tend not to get the attention they deserve in part due to the relative complexity of the stories that explore them. I’m curious to see if the Panama Leaks and the associated coverage have made a breakthrough and mainstreamed these issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had a look at Google Trends which lets you compare the popularity of certain search terms over time, a decent metric of the level of public interest in a given topic. The immediate effect on awareness of the related issues is clear, but how this translates into concrete reform, behaviour change and what people demand at the ballot box is yet to be seen. Surely though, there is reason to be optimistic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot; src=&quot;//www.google.co.uk/trends/embed.js?hl=en-US&amp;amp;q=%22tax+evasion%22,+%22tax+avoidance%22&amp;amp;cmpt=q&amp;amp;tz=Etc/GMT-1&amp;amp;tz=Etc/GMT-1&amp;amp;content=1&amp;amp;cid=TIMESERIES_GRAPH_0&amp;amp;export=5&amp;amp;w=780&amp;amp;h=330&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s notable that “tax avoidance” as a search term had a significant spike in June 2012 when Jimmy Carr’s use of a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.theguardian.com/business/2012/jun/19/tax-scheme-jimmy-carr-hmrc&quot;&gt;“K2” tax avoidance scheme&lt;/a&gt; received press attention. As ever, the celebrity status  of the scalp claimed in the exposé drives public interest.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 10 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>https://blog.noelmas.net/2016/04/10/tax-trends/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.noelmas.net/2016/04/10/tax-trends/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Is the NHS safe in Cameron&#39;s hands?</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;As the government’s increasingly bitter dispute with Junior Doctors rolls on to the backdrop of a critically overstretched health service, it’s difficult to see how David Cameron can back up his words during the 2015 election campaign that NHS is &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.itv.com/news/update/2015-05-18/david-cameron-the-nhs-is-safe-in-my-hands/&quot;&gt;“safe in my hands”&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Data published by NHS England appears to show A&amp;amp;E waiting times slipping to new lows as patients in need of emergency care wait longer to be admitted to hospital.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the hallmarks of the the New Labour years was a focus on performance targets in public service particualry the NHS. This drew criticism from Conservatives and accusations of public sector bodies gaming the system. It’s interesting to observe that when it comes to A&amp;amp;E waiting times, a loosening of targets has coincided with a steep drop in the number of patients waiting less than 4 hours in A&amp;amp;E.[1]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Coalition government on taking the reigns in 2010 reduced the target for the proportion of A&amp;amp;E attendees being seen in under 4 hours from 98% to 95%. Despite the lower bar, the NHS under the Conservatives appears unable to achieve this as demonstrated by the chart below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&quot;//datawrapper.dwcdn.net/ivf9S/1/&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowtransparency=&quot;true&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;allowfullscreen&quot; webkitallowfullscreen=&quot;webkitallowfullscreen&quot; mozallowfullscreen=&quot;mozallowfullscreen&quot; oallowfullscreen=&quot;oallowfullscreen&quot; msallowfullscreen=&quot;msallowfullscreen&quot; width=&quot;748&quot; height=&quot;400&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is a similar story when it comes to the number of patients waiting 12 hours or more from decision to admit to admission.  Although still relatively small, the numbers have been steadily rising since 2010, with an unexplained spike in December 2014.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://charts.datawrapper.de/6OOHu/index.html&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowtransparency=&quot;true&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;allowfullscreen&quot; webkitallowfullscreen=&quot;webkitallowfullscreen&quot; mozallowfullscreen=&quot;mozallowfullscreen&quot; oallowfullscreen=&quot;oallowfullscreen&quot; msallowfullscreen=&quot;msallowfullscreen&quot; width=&quot;748&quot; height=&quot;400&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In poking around the public data available on NHS performance, I found a worrying lack of consistency in the reporting between administrations. On top of this, the A&amp;amp;E waiting list data pre-2010 appears not to have been properly archived and as such is no longer available to the public. These historical data gaps make it harder to compare the performance of subsequent governments and truly assess key election pledges around the protection of essential public services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In any case, the data that is available and in-depth studies of it by &lt;a href=&quot;http://qmr.kingsfund.org.uk/2016/18/&quot;&gt;groups like the King’s Fund&lt;/a&gt; [2] paint a damning picture that put the lie to Cameron’s “safe in my hands” line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[1] Have targets improved NHS performance? - The King’s Fund &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.kingsfund.org.uk/projects/general-election-2010/key-election-questions/performance-targets&quot;&gt;http://www.kingsfund.org.uk/projects/general-election-2010/key-election-questions/performance-targets&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[2] How is the NHS performing? - The King’s Fund &lt;a href=&quot;http://qmr.kingsfund.org.uk/2016/18/&quot;&gt;http://qmr.kingsfund.org.uk/2016/18/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/article&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 22 Mar 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://blog.noelmas.net/open/data/2016/03/22/safe-in-my-hands/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.noelmas.net/open/data/2016/03/22/safe-in-my-hands/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Open data at Global Witness in 2016</title>
        <description>&lt;em&gt;Cross-posted for the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.globalwitness.org/en/blog/open-data-can-make-world-better-place-only-if-we-know-how-use-it/&quot;&gt;Global Witness blog&lt;/a&gt; where it was first published.&lt;/em&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;aligned intro&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;rich-text&quot;&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;p&gt;I’m a self-confessed data junkie, but I appreciate that spreadsheets aren’t everyone’s idea of fun. Most people want their digested data packaged up into compelling stories and beautiful visuals. My job here at Global Witness is to do exactly that - tooling up the organisation and its partners so that we can take the troves of data we have access to and ask the questions of it that will help us create positive change.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;aligned&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;rich-text&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Now is a very exciting time to be doing this. As the explosion of powerful, free data analysis tools intersects with our own efforts to bring business into the open, we’re seeing exciting new opportunities to help cut poverty and financial crime all over the world. The challenge, as we see it, is to find the right tools and equip the right people so that all this information can be translated into genuine accountability for those in power.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;There is already a lot of valuable data relevant to our mission in the public domain. For example, billions of dollars worth of company-to-government payments are now published each year as part of the Publish What You Pay initiative that Global Witness helped to found. Elsewhere, recent US legislation means thousands of companies who use minerals in their products routinely publish information on their supply chains, to make sure they aren’t sponsoring conflict or bloodshed where the raw materials are mined.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As well as laws demanding information be published, there are non-profit organisations which exist to collect data and make it useful. &lt;a href=&quot;https://opencorporates.com/&quot;&gt;OpenCorporates&lt;/a&gt;, the world’s largest free database of corporate data, now contains the records of over of 97 million companies from around the world. MySociety’s nascent &lt;a href=&quot;http://everypolitician.org/&quot;&gt;EveryPolitician.org &lt;/a&gt;contains the records of over 60,000 politicians from over 232 companies which have been scraped and crowdsourced from numerous digital sources. Our friends at OpenOil now have a service which provides free access over one million company filings related to the oil, gas and mining industries.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;figure style=&quot;display:inline-block;text-align:center;float:right&quot;&gt;	
&lt;img src=&quot;https://globalwitness.org/media/images/Screen_Shot_2016-02-17_at_16.10.14.width-300.png&quot; width=&quot;300&quot; height=&quot;162&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; style=&quot;vertical-align:top&quot;/&gt;
&lt;figcaption style=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;p style=&quot;font-size:8px&quot;&gt;Visualisation from Open Oil&#39;s &lt;br&gt; vast database of contracts from Nigeria&#39;s byzantine &lt;br&gt; oil industry: &lt;a href=&quot;https://data.openoil.net/#nigeria_production&quot;&gt;https://data.openoil.net/#nigeria_production&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;aligned&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;rich-text&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;This data could revolutionise the way journalists and NGOs like Global Witness expose the corrupt networks that deprive some of the world’s poorest people of the wealth beneath their feet. But for that to happen, the data needs to be actively monitored and mined by groups equipped with the right skills and tools. This analysis is especially valuable in states with limited political will or capacity to undertake their own corruption investigations, as is the case in many countries where Global Witness works. So the opportunities are obvious, but it’s complicated.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;No single public dataset is likely to unearth substantial corruption on its own. The real value tends to come when these datasets are combined in ways not anticipated by the publisher. For example, combining port records with company information has allowed us to show how the EU’s demand for illegal timber from the DRC undermines efforts to protect the world’s second largest rainforest. Elsewhere, company filings from multiple jurisdictions helped piece together the corrupt and complex deal behind the sale of Nigeria’s largest oil block, which deprived its citizens of over one billion US dollars. The more data that is available on companies and governments in a standardised form, the greater the opportunity for linking this information in meaningful ways to fight corruption.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;figure style=&quot;display:inline-block;text-align:center&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://globalwitness.org/media/images/Screen_Shot_2016-02-17_at_15.48.22.width-1280.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;/&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;
&lt;p style=&quot;font-size:8px&quot;&gt;A screenshot of Global Witness’s Timber Trade Tracker built in collaboration with &lt;a href=&quot;http://okfn.org/&quot;&gt;Open Knowledge&lt;/a&gt; that visualises the flows of illegal timber out of the DRC. The data is updated on a quarterly basis: &lt;a href=&quot;http://drctimbertracker.globalwitness.org/&quot;&gt;http://drctimbertracker.globalwitness.org/ &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;aligned&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;rich-text&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;How do we stop all this data from becoming an overwhelming deluge of information? This is where the tools developed by civic hackers and socially minded tech firms come in. Take the tools for cross-checking lists of names against databases of “politically exposed people” (PEPs) now being developed by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.occrp.org/en&quot;&gt;OCCRP&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href=&quot;http://influencemapping.org/&quot;&gt;Influence Mapping&lt;/a&gt; community. These are invaluable instruments in identifying conflicts of interest and corruption in the allocation of lucrative natural resources. Free software like &lt;a href=&quot;http://openrefine.org/&quot;&gt;OpenRefine&lt;/a&gt; puts powerful data processing algorithms at the fingertips of non-programmers and tools like &lt;a href=&quot;http://pandas.pydata.org/&quot;&gt;Python-Pandas&lt;/a&gt; , initially developed for the finance industries but now open source, let people manipulate spreadsheets millions of rows long. We put these tools to use in combination in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.globalwitness.org/en-gb/campaigns/oil-gas-and-mining/myanmarjade/&quot;&gt;our recent Myanmar jade investigation&lt;/a&gt;, using &lt;a href=&quot;http://opencorporates.com&quot;&gt;OpenCorporates&lt;/a&gt; data to help show how this vast trade is monopolised by a military elite at the expense of some of Myanmar’s most vulnerable people.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;figure style=&quot;display:inline-block;text-align:center;float:left&quot;&gt;	
&lt;img src=&quot;https://globalwitness.org/media/images/The-Great-Rip-Off-The-BVI-Effect-copy.width-300.jpg&quot; width=&quot;300&quot; height=&quot;162&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; style=&quot;vertical-align:top&quot;/&gt;
&lt;figcaption style=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;p style=&quot;font-size:8px&quot;&gt;Secrecy for sale in the British Virgin Islands as &lt;br&gt; visualised in our &lt;a href=&quot;http://greatripoffmap.globalwitness.org/#!/&quot;&gt;Great Rip Off Map&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;aligned&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;rich-text&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;That’s not to say we shouldn’t also work tirelessly to improve the data that’s already out there. Existing sources of public data are far from perfect, and in many countries online access to public records still remains a distant dream. Lack of standardisation makes information difficult to retrieve and connect. The secrecy for sale in the world’s tax havens means that many corporate structures used to funnel the proceeds of corruption remain hidden. Global Witness will continue to push for those gaps to be filled and input into developing strong, open and workable standards along with our partners in groups such as &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.publishwhatyoupay.org/&quot;&gt;Publish What You Pay&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href=&quot;https://financialtransparency.org/&quot;&gt;Financial Transparency&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.open-contracting.org/&quot;&gt;Open Contracting&lt;/a&gt; coalitions. And alongside our data work, we will be lobbying decision-makers to ensure that transparency becomes the expected norm in how the world does its business.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The open data revolution shows no sign of slowing in 2016. This year even more data will go online as hundreds of UK companies release project-level information on all payments to governments in the oil, gas and mining industries under new EU law. From July onwards all UK companies will be forced to publish who their real owners are in publicly accessible register, something that Global Witness has been fighting for many years.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;figure style=&quot;display:inline-block;text-align:center;float:right&quot;&gt;	
&lt;img src=&quot;https://globalwitness.org/media/images/Screen_Shot_2016-02-17_at_16.19.47_EY9qJg2.width-300.png&quot; width=&quot;300&quot; height=&quot;162&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; style=&quot;vertical-align:top&quot;/&gt;
&lt;figcaption style=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;p style=&quot;font-size:8px&quot;&gt;OpenCorporates&#39; proof-of-concept of a global beneficial &lt;br&gt;ownership registry: &lt;a href=&quot;http://alpha.whocontrolsit.com/&quot;&gt;http://alpha.whocontrolsit.com/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;aligned&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;rich-text&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;For anyone who wants to fight corruption and build a more open, just society, this is really exciting. For a data geek like me, it’s doubly so. But as the possibilities grow, so does the work involved in mining all the data, and we’re far from the only ones driving this. This week in Lima, I’ll be working with activists from all over the world to look at how they can apply these tools and techniques to their different contexts, and help make sure the new availability of information brings justice and accountability from their governments. Together we’ll be trawling this new information for insights and leads, so that the individuals and systems that perpetuate conflict, corruption and environmental devastation have no place to hide.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Watch this space!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 20 Feb 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://blog.noelmas.net/open/data/2016/02/20/gw-in-2016/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.noelmas.net/open/data/2016/02/20/gw-in-2016/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Ingredients of an open data investigation</title>
        <description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;background-to-investigation&quot;&gt;Background to investigation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The jade industry in Burma was worth a staggering $31 billion in 2014 - equivalent to half of Burma’s official GDP. &lt;a href=&quot;https://globalwitness.org&quot;&gt;Global Witness&lt;/a&gt; undertook a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.globalwitness.org/en-gb/campaigns/oil-gas-and-mining/myanmarjade/&quot;&gt;year-long investigation&lt;/a&gt; to tell the story of this valuable mineral and who really benefits from it. The picture that emerged was a grim one: jade is secretly controlled by Burma’s military elite and some of the generals associated with the worst abuses of junta rule. Little or no money flows to the communities who live in jade mining regions where some of Burma’s poorest and most vulnerable people live.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The team working on this used a variety of investigative approaches including field research, interviews and economic analysis.  One important aspect of the work was data analysis conducted using publicly available company data published by &lt;a href=&quot;https://opencorporates.com/&quot;&gt;OpenCorporates&lt;/a&gt;. By combining this data with other sources, we were able to understand the complex webs of ownership of the jade industry and which individuals and groups controlled this valuable mineral.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The approach could in principle be applied to many other investigations. Below is a description of the method used, so that it might give other groups seeking to undertake similar analysis using OpenCorporates a place to start.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;data-acquisition&quot;&gt;Data acquisition&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The research began with a government map of jade concessions and their current license holders. As our goal was to understand who was behind these companies, we needed to get this data in a form that could be linked to a database like OpenCorporates. This needed to be (a) in a structured form that could programatically be linked to another database, and (b) in English. So the first step was to create a simple Excel spreadsheet and translate these names into English using Roman script.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;reconciliation-with-opencorporates-api&quot;&gt;Reconciliation with OpenCorporates API&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Transliteration always introduces some ambiguity and there are often numerous ways to convert a specific company name from one script to another. Fortunately, OpenCorporates has a service that lets users find company names in the database that are near but not exact matches. This all happens via an &lt;a href=&quot;https://api.opencorporates.com/documentation/Open-Refine-Reconciliation-API&quot;&gt;‘endpoint’&lt;/a&gt; through which users can load the data they want to reconcile into &lt;a href=&quot;http://openrefine.org/&quot;&gt;OpenRefine&lt;/a&gt;. OpenCorporates will then return a likely set of matches against the company names you have imported. In the case of this investigation, many of the companies returned multiple matches. The mining, gems and trading arms of companies were often separated into different legal entities under the same name. Take for example, Max Burma Company: there is a &lt;a href=&quot;https://opencorporates.com/companies/mm/733-1993-1994&quot;&gt;general limited company&lt;/a&gt;, a &lt;a href=&quot;https://opencorporates.com/companies/mm/903-2007-2008&quot;&gt;gems and jewellery arm&lt;/a&gt; as well as a &lt;a href=&quot;https://opencorporates.com/companies/mm/958-2005-2006&quot;&gt;construction company&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each set of results was checked by the team of researchers and the best matches were chosen and added to the data, now with a link to the OpenCorporates database. This was a painstaking task even with the suggestions all the automation OpenRefine supplied, there was still a lot of human judgement required.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;extraction-of-shareholders-and-director-data&quot;&gt;Extraction of shareholders and director data&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that relationships had been established between the jade companies and the OpenCorporates database, we were in a position to extract other properties of those companies held within OpenCorporates. The properties of primary interest were shareholders and directors of those companies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are a number of ways to extract this information, one could write a script in a language like Python to programmatically query the &lt;a href=&quot;https://api.opencorporates.com/&quot;&gt;OpenCorporates API&lt;/a&gt; for instance. The method we opted for was to use the data we already had in OpenRefine and extract the new information we needed into new columns from OpenCorporates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;extracting-shareholder-sand-directors-from-opencorporates-using-openrefine&quot;&gt;Extracting shareholder sand directors from OpenCorporates using OpenRefine&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Load in the company names for which you want to extract shareholders and directors intro OpenRefine;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Reconcile the names to the OpenCorporates API, you can follow the tutorial available &lt;a href=&quot;https://api.opencorporates.com/documentation/Google-Refine-Reconciliation-API&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Once you have reconciled the data and chosen the correct matches, you need to add a column to your data that contains the OpenCorporates ID. This can be achieved by clicking Edit Column &amp;gt; Add column based on this column in the Transform box type &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;cell.recon.match.id&lt;/code&gt;;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You should now have a column with the OpenCorporates ID. From this you can construct a URL which returns JSON data for each company on its shareholders and directors;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You now need to add a column in which we will get data that contains our officers and our shareholders. First, we construct a column that contains the URLs which will return this data;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;For the Burmese company registry you need to construct two different URLs. The director data is contained within the JSON you get from calling &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&quot;http://api.opencorporates.com&quot; + cell.recon.match.id&lt;/code&gt;. The shareholder data on the other hand is contained within the JSON you get from the URL &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&quot;http://api.opencorporates.com&quot; + cell.recon.match.id + &quot;/statements&quot;&lt;/code&gt;;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We now have two nicely formatted columns containing the URLs we need. Copy and paste one of them into a browser, you should see some data about that company. If it looks messy, install a JSON viewer plug-in in your browser like &lt;a href=&quot;https://chrome.google.com/webstore/detail/jsonview/chklaanhfefbnpoihckbnefhakgolnmc?hl=en&quot;&gt;JSONView for Chrome&lt;/a&gt;;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Next we pull all the data returned by each of these URLs by using Refine’s fetch URL function. We can access this by going to one of our URL columns and clicking Edit columns &amp;gt; Add column by fetching URLs;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Depending on how much data you want to extract, you may need to add an API Token to your URLs. You can request an open data API token from OpenCorporates which lets you request 10,000 URLs a day. When you fetch your URLs you can add it to you URLs by typing value &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;+ “&amp;amp;api_token=”&lt;/code&gt; in the expression box;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;OpenRefine will then work through you your URLs returning JSON formatted data in the cells in your new column. Once this process has finished you then need to parse this data and extract the relevant bits. In the case of the Burma investigation we were interested in two key pieces of data for directors - their names and their national identifier number. This is the code we used to extract this: 
  &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;forEach(value.parseJson()
  .get(&quot;results&quot;).company
  .officers,v,(v.officer.name + &quot; (&quot; + v.officer.position + &quot;)&quot; + &quot; (&quot; + v.officer.uid + &quot;)&quot;))
  .join(&quot;:::&quot;)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;fuzzy-matching-of-directors-against-sanctions-lists&quot;&gt;Fuzzy matching of directors against sanctions lists&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An important part of the investigation was to understand if any of the directors of jade mining companies or their directors were under sanctions for any reason. By this time we had the names of thousands of companies, directors and shareholders. While there are various proprietary databases for checking this information like LexisNexis or WorldCheck, few of them let you programmatically search for such large numbers of names at once. We therefore opted for our own solution using existing sources of public data [1].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We took a number of recent sanctions lists published by the &lt;a href=&quot;http://eeas.europa.eu/cfsp/sanctions/consol-list/index_en.htm&quot;&gt;EU&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.treasury.gov/resource-center/sanctions/Programs/Pages/Programs.aspx&quot;&gt;US&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://dfat.gov.au/international-relations/security/sanctions/pages/consolidated-list.aspx&quot;&gt;Australia&lt;/a&gt;. We then sought to match these names with the names of company officers and shareholders from OpenCorporates. Names are often spelt differently, so rather than looking for exact matches we used a technique called ‘fuzzy matching’.  There are a number of different ways to fuzzy match names. We opted to use a Python scripts to do this [2], but you can also try to use tools such as &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.microsoft.com/en-gb/download/details.aspx?id=15011&quot;&gt;Microsoft Excel’s Fuzzy Lookup&lt;/a&gt; addin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;checking-for-politically-exposed-directors-using-national-identifiers&quot;&gt;Checking for politically exposed directors using national identifiers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the objectives of the investigation was to look at the extent to which politicians in Burma had interests in the jade industry. Making associations between political figures via name alone was difficult for two main reasons. First, our list of shareholders and officers was already in the hundreds and manual cross checking would be very time consuming. Second, many Burmese individuals share the same surname so a match based on name alone does not guarantee by any means that the two individuals you are looking at are the same.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is where the national identifiers published first by &lt;a href=&quot;http://dica.gov.mm.x-aas.net/&quot;&gt;DICA&lt;/a&gt;, the Burmese company registry, and re-published by OpenCorporates were so useful. We were able to build up our own lists of Burmese PEPs (“Politically Exposed People”) using national identifiers of political candidates published in Burmese newspapers and available online. Historical copies of the newspaper the New Light of Burma Times (for example this issue &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.globalwitness.org/en-gb/campaigns/oil-gas-and-mining/myanmarjade/&quot;&gt;published on 13 Nov 2010&lt;/a&gt;) proved particularly useful&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, we used “fuzzy” rather than exact matching. We looked for national identifiers that were the same but with one or two characters difference. We were able to catch those individuals where ID numbers had been put in incorrectly through clerical error, and, more interestingly, associate them with members of their family that had successive ID numbers. On one occasion the spouse of a Burmese politician who had the national identifier after her husband (presumably they had registered together).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;lessons-learned&quot;&gt;Lessons learned&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The methodology above provided us with a number of connections between jade companies and the Burmese military that were later incorporated into the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.globalwitness.org/en-gb/campaigns/oil-gas-and-mining/myanmarjade/&quot;&gt;final report&lt;/a&gt; published in November 2015.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are some key lessons that we have taken from this approach:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Open source tools are key for public integrity journalism&lt;/em&gt; - We could not have cleaned and processed the data without tools like OpenRefine that supply simple graphical interfaces, power and flexibility in a way that is affordable to those working in the not-for-profit sector.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Unique identifiers are essential&lt;/em&gt;- We would not have been able to conclusively connect members of the military elite to the jade industry without the national identifier numbers.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;OpenCorporates supports powerful workflows not available for common proprietary databases&lt;/em&gt; - While databases like Orbis may have more complete information they do not support the bulk data operations and flexible workflows required for this investigation. The OpenCorporates API proved invaluable at every step from reconciling the company names to harvesting director data in bulk. [3]&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;*The importance of scraped data *- At the time of undertaking the investigation the original source of the company data (&lt;a href=&quot;http://dica.gov.mm.x-aas.net/&quot;&gt;DICA&lt;/a&gt;) was not available. This is where OpenCorporates again proved its value with its vast archive of scraped data preserving access public interest data even when the original publishers have taken it down. [3]&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Data journalism projects requires dedication (and perspiration!)&lt;/em&gt; - Even with all the powerful computational tools we had at our disposal, there was still a huge amount of manual data cleaning and reviewing required to get reliable results.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[1] Friedrich Lindenberg has made the first baby steps towards pulling together an open source PEP list that may be useful for those undertaking similar cross-checking exercises: &lt;a href=&quot;http://pudo.org/material/opennames/&quot;&gt;http://pudo.org/material/opennames/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[2] Our Python approach to fuzzy matching used a method to this &lt;a href=&quot;http://blog.yhat.com/posts/fuzzy-matching-with-yhat.html&quot;&gt;http://blog.yhat.com/posts/fuzzy-matching-with-yhat.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[3] The team at OpenCorporates explore these issues more fully in their white paper on the subject, &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@opencorporates/how-open-company-data-was-used-to-uncover-the-powerful-elite-benefiting-from-myanmar-s-multi-1ef35f88d6bd#.ygcs3g3i9&quot;&gt;“How open company data was used to uncover the powerful elite benefiting from Burma’s multi-billion dollar jade industry”&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 15 Feb 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://blog.noelmas.net/investigations/2016/02/15/opencorproates-jade-investigation/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.noelmas.net/investigations/2016/02/15/opencorproates-jade-investigation/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Scraping PDF tables using ScraperWiki and Open Refine</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Lots has been written as to why the PDF is inadequate format for data publication.&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#1&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; PDFs aren’t machine readable and information from them often can’t even be copy and pasted. Despite this governments, corporations and multi-lateral organisations still release large amounts of public data as PDF. As a result, any organisation or individual wanting to analyse public data will have to extract structured data from PDFs at some point. A fantastic tool for doing this - and which requires no coding knowledge at all - is &lt;a href=&quot;http://scraperwiki.com&quot;&gt;ScraperWiki’s&lt;/a&gt; PDF table extract tool.&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#2&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; In combination with the data cleaning tool, &lt;a href=&quot;http://openrefine.org/&quot;&gt;Open Refine&lt;/a&gt;, you can wrangle most PDFs into an analysable form within minutes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The screencast below shows one method to turn the PDF of a UK investment sanctions list for Burmese companies into a spreadsheet. This kind of transformation would be useful if you wanted to automatically reconcile the list of companies with an external database such as &lt;a href=&quot;https://opencorporates.com/&quot;&gt;OpenCorporates&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#3&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; see if any of organsiations appear in another dataset you’ve been compiling or map the locations of the companies. For this demo, we are aiming to create a spreadsheet that contains one organisation name and address per row. The screencast and instructions below walk through the steps:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;object width=&quot;100%&quot;&gt;&lt;param name=&quot;movie&quot; value=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/v/GobC87hVvrQ&amp;amp;hl=en&amp;amp;fs=1&quot; /&gt;&lt;param name=&quot;allowFullScreen&quot; value=&quot;true&quot; /&gt;&lt;embed src=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/v/GobC87hVvrQ&amp;amp;hl=en&amp;amp;fs=1&quot; type=&quot;application/x-shockwave-flash&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;true&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;500&quot; /&gt;&lt;/object&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Log-in to &lt;a href=&quot;http://scraperwiki.com&quot;&gt;ScraperWiki&lt;/a&gt; (create a free account if you don’t have one already), create a new dataset and choose the PDF Extract tool&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Upload your PDF or paste in a web link to your PDF if it’s available publicly. For the purposes of this demo we will be using the sanctions list at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.betterregulation.com/external/investmentban.pdf&quot;&gt;http://www.betterregulation.com/external/investmentban.pdf&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Download All Tables as an Excel spreadsheet&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Open the spreadsheet in Excel, there will be a tab for each page of data in the PDF&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Remove the header and footer information on each tab from each page&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Start Open Refine and create a project with your spreadsheet&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In preview mode, load each of the tabs that contains the data you are interested by ticking them (for brevity I’ve only turn the first 3 tabs)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In preview mode, our data does not have headers so untick the “Parse next X lines(s) as column headers”&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Open Refine recognises each of our lines from the table as a record despite the fact that it flows over multiple spreadsheet rows. As we are aiming to produce a spreadsheet with one organisation per line, we need to re-shape our data so the rows from our record that display “Organisation name” and “Address” have their own columns.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On “Column 2” choose the “Add a column based on this column function”. Insert the following bit of Google Refine Expressions Language (GREL):&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt; row.record.cells[&quot;Column 2&quot;][0].value
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Do this a second time except changing the 0 to a 1:&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt; row.record.cells[&quot;Column 2&quot;][1].value
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The newly created “Address” column retains some extra information that is not useful this time such as “Other information” (you may want to put this data into a new column). We are going to remove it. We would struggle to do this using a normal Find and Replace operation as the string we want to replace is different for every cell, however it does follow a pattern so we are able to use Regular Expressions.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In the “Address” column go to “Edit cells &amp;gt; Transform”, insert the following GREL expression that effectively finds all strings in that column that start with “Other information:” and are followed by an indefinite number of further characters. Regular Expressions are bounded by the “/” character in GREL:&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt; value.replace(/\sOther\sInformation.*/,&quot;&quot;)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Now to get remove the extra lines in the records, so that we only have one line for each row of data.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Choose the “Edit Cells &amp;gt; Blank down” function on the “Address” column effectively blanking out all consecutive duplicate rows for that column&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Go to “Facet &amp;gt; Text Facet” on the “Address column”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Select from the Text Facet box “(blank)”, we need to remove all these rows&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Change the view (top left) to “Rows” from “Records”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;From the “All” function drop down (top left) select “Edit Cells &amp;gt; Remove all matching rows”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Finally, export you project using the button in the top right to either an Excel or CSV file. We now have the one row one record structure we were looking for. You can clean up your data furthers by taking out&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;1&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;[1] See for example &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.scraperwiki.com/2013/12/the-tyranny-of-the-pdf/&quot;&gt;https://blog.scraperwiki.com/2013/12/the-tyranny-of-the-pdf/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;2&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;[2] ScraperWiki appears to be spinning this tool out as a separate product called &lt;a href=&quot;https://pdftables.com/&quot;&gt;PDF Tables&lt;/a&gt;, but you can still access the tool through ScraperWiki when this was written.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;3&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;[3] If you&#39;re interested in reconciling company names to the OpenCorporates database in order to attach the wealth information held by OpenCorporates to your database (e.g. director names, date of incorporation etc) take a look at &lt;a href=&quot;http://vimeo.com/17924204&quot;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; tutorial.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 21 Dec 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://blog.noelmas.net/ddj-tips/scraping/2014/12/21/scraperwiki-pdf-extract-openrefine/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.noelmas.net/ddj-tips/scraping/2014/12/21/scraperwiki-pdf-extract-openrefine/</guid>
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
